hello everyone
it's July 4th 2023
and we're in our first discussion on
chapter two
so
let us head over there
and before we jump into anything
specific
um does anyone have any
General
Reflections or or thoughts on chapter
two
just any any pieces that stuck with them
from their reading or
just overall reflections
from chapter two
on the low road
yes if I could go I'm not sure whether
yeah please
um
I was curious in terms of the equations
uh
that relate to free energy so the
manifestations of free energy in those
three or four equations
mathematically how are those derived
because in the textbook they kind of
just seem to be
axiomatically
um placed there but I was wondering what
is the underlying mathematical root of
those equations from which we work
thanks Ollie
thank you yeah the derivations are the
four equations at least 2.5 and uh 2.6
is
um I mean we've done basically uh
complete steps for the derivations of
each of those equations and
I'll upload a file explaining each step
after the meeting if you want but I'm
not sure where to put the files uh
Daniel could you please uh
I mean where do you think would be most
helpful to put those files file format
is it
uh it's a PDF so what one option is to
just at the top of the notes you could
always just drag in a PDF
or I just drop it here another option is
to um in the GitHub
repo for the textbook
to add it there in some format
um but yeah certainly dropping a PDF or
taking screenshots in here would be
awesome
but yeah this is this is a great
question
and one more thing about the derivations
of those Central equations is uh they're
not necessarily uh
evidence from the textbook or the way
they're expressed in the textbook how we
can get from each line of the equations
to the next line so I agree we need some
intermediary steps and even we need to
employ some mathematical
um some mathematical theorisms theorems
and rules such as Jane's inequality rule
to get to some of those equations
but I hope I mean the derivations we've
worked out would be helpful if people
want to follow the exact details of each
derivation
yeah that's awesome work with um Ali and
Jonathan
and Jacob also did some of these
preliminary
um connections for a few of the
equations
cool
oh and we're gonna come to to these
equations and we'll talk about them a
lot more soon but any other just overall
chapter two
thoughts or or
reflections
um
at the
something that was interesting to me
is there's kind of a however loose
identification between an agent an
active inference and their priors this
is pulling from page 39. that we can say
in active inference the identity of an
agent is isomorphic with its priors or
the relationship between
I suppose the the agent and their their
preferences
yeah the priors are
what the thing
brings through the needle of the present
to confront the incoming observation to
then be updated
into the posterior but then that just
becomes the prior for the next moment so
like if it's not coming with you through
the priors
it's not making it through the
bottleneck of the presence
it has been forgotten
so everything has to come through the
presence
in order for the past to influence the
future that's like the markovian
property of like a Markov chain
so that Markov blanket necessarily but
actually that is a markup blanket
through time
past only influences the future through
the present
so everything has to flow through the
present in order to have influence
but that is a very interesting
claim
any other um
thought thoughts or ideas on two just
overall
cool we'll we'll look at some questions
but just the big picture for the next
month I guess for all of July
two weeks on chapter two that's the low
road
and then two weeks on chapter three
that's gonna be the high road
so first we're going to talk about how
and this is going to get us from the
basic
tautologically true Bayesian theorem
all the way on through
heuristics that are used to fit
Bayesian models of perception and action
that's going to get us to active
inference and then we're going to kind
of like take a breath reset start not
from the how on the low road but the why
on the high road and that's going to get
us to the same place
and then that will drop us off at
chapter four which is going to be like
another level of depth into the
generative model
that is used at active inference
um first I'll just check
Okay cool so I'm going to chapter two
specific
um questions for cohort four you can
just follow the little um
token if you want okay
all right
why does the minimization of Divergence
not also lead to the maximization of
model evidence
are you not generating new accurate
priors that are evidenced by the
incoming sensorium
so if the person who asked this is here
they can unpack a little bit or anyone
else can provide a thought or an idea on
this
yeah so I wrote this just uh with an eye
on the equation
um let me be good to get it after
possible because no worries if not
um which has the kind of
action perception
um
dual aspect so the first bit is
perception with the KO Divergence and
the second verse with action
um
my question therefore is if we are
getting closer to Optimal Bayesian
inference would you lowering the bound
on free energy
surely optimizing or getting close to
Optimal Bayesian inferences therefore
driving us to update our priors in a way
that would be
the way that basically perfectly reduces
prediction error
and therefore minimizes free energy so I
wasn't sure whether is it just that in
reality action and perception are always
coupled or is there uh is there
something you know is there a limit to
optimizing perceptual inference
yeah great
um topics which equation were you
referencing just so we can look at it so
it's so if you go back on the textbook
um it's worth so it's on 2.5
and that it's the last one I've uh so if
you keep going I'm sorry 2.6 um yeah so
it's the Divergence evidence one yeah
yeah okay okay okay great all right
equation 2.5 variational free energy
okay so first just to just to give a
thought again anyone can raise their
hand up if they if they want to add more
um
the minimization of Divergence
does lead to the maximization of model
evidence
so the the um
um relationship to keep in mind is that
the model with the most evidence for it
is going to be the one that minimizes
surprise
minimization of surprise is itself
intractable and so we use this bounding
approximation which is the expected for
energy so let's think about this with
the heights of the children in the
classroom
so we want to have the maximum evidence
estimation for the heights of the
children in the classroom that's like
the ultimate statistical problem that we
want to solve
now if we had the model parameterization
that minimized our surprise so as new
heights were drawn we were minimally
surprised that would be equivalent to
having the maximum evidence model
and then surprise itself which is just
like the log of P that is intractable
and that's why we have a bounding
function
so the minimization of Divergence is
used
um as a attractable way
to because this is going to be a
constant
with respect to Q
so in terms of the the distribution that
we actually control the knobs on Q
this is not going to have
um any gradient to it
and so that's why variational free
energy can be incrementally optimized by
reducing the KL Divergence here
[Music]
um
and you are generating priors
that are uh you're you're updating
priors based upon incoming sensory data
I'll just note though that action is not
included in this equation
this is purely a functional so it's a
function of a function
it's a functional variational free
energy of Q the distribution that we
control variational approximator and the
data y
but there's no action selection here
anyone else want to add a thought on
this
um yeah Ali thanks
well actually uh this Duality between
the minimization of the free energy on
one hand and maximizing the evidence
afforded by the generative model and the
other is what usually referred to as uh
self-evidencing mechanism after Jakob
Howie's well-known paper from 2014 or 16
I guess
so uh the idea is that uh well I mean a
particle and by particle I mean
The Joint set of internal and blanket
states of a system uh will look as if it
is gathering evidence for its own
generative model and where it's
generative model also entails the prior
belief that uh that it um it's somehow
acts upon upon later by choosing proper
uh sets of uh I mean policy and by
policy I mean a set of actions uh
selected by
um the agent or the particle as somehow
minimizing the expected free energy at
this time so variation of free energy
provides a kind of
um
a kind of upper limit to
uh to to the way that uh the agent tries
to minimize its perceptual
uncertainties but then later on in order
to effectuate that uncertainties and to
uh kind of have causal intervention onto
the environment then it needs to select
a policy in order to minimize its
expected free energy so in this sense
both variational free energy unexpected
free energy can be seen as parallel or
dual to each other and we can obviously
see from the form of the equations of
2.5 and 2.6 that they're actually
mathematically and formally are parallel
thanks
another way to to
um see this is like we're gonna come
back to it
um multiple times but variational free
energy
is like the real-time perceptual how's
it going
because it is purely inferential it's
real time as a functional of beliefs and
incoming data so if we're talking about
body temperature and homeostasis
this is just like
how the body temperature is and so we
kind of latch our model's performance
and the the desire to not under or over
fit that is latched to the ultimate
observable layer
with incoming data
but this is a passive equation
but this this is the same
variational free energy that you would
see in a variational autoencoder
so if you had a some Bayesian statistics
problem
and you're just trying to
um interpolate
um pixels in a variational autoencoder
you wouldn't want to over under fit this
is exactly what you would have
and then in order to have causal
efficacy and the imperative there just
like mentioned
this is going to be a constant term with
respect to Q
so we can minimize the Divergence this
KL Divergence which is always bigger
than zero
and that pushes down F towards surprise
if we had the minimally surprising model
we'd have the model with the most
evidence
and then in 2.6 we get into causal
efficacy in a sort of prospective way
Young
that's just a I think it's a minor issue
but
because because our ZIP objective is to
lower the variation of free energy
it seems to me like it's better to
explain surprise as the lower bound of
variational free energy rather than
seeing that the variation of the energy
is the upper bounds
because well the our objective is to
reduce these cable Librarians of 2x with
the posterior so that the free energy
itself can be minimized to the surprise
itself so I think it's more intuitive to
explain
as surprise being the lower bound of the
variational free energy
yeah that's that's a good point and also
once you start doing oh well there's
negative f
and and so the upper and the lower
I I I think whichever way you you want
to approach this um
this Divergence from
when the KL Divergence is minimized
then the distance between these two
distributions is lower
sorry not the distance the Divergence
the only difference between a Divergence
and a distance in this setting is like a
distance is the same from A to B as B to
a
and it turns out the KL doesn't have
that property which is why it's called
the diversion it's not a distance
um however when variational free energy
is minimized
then the approximating belief function Q
with respect to the incoming data
are doing as well as they can at
bounding surprise
that's the best fitting model with the
most evidence I mean if you knew
optimally how surprised to be by uh what
was going to happen next in the movie
you would have the best model of what
was about to happen in the movie
and so maximum model evidence
can be
approached by minimizing surprise
minimizing surprise is itself
intractable compute so we minimize
abound on surprise which is the
variational free energy Ali
actually that's uh exactly the elbow or
evidence lower bound as encountered in
RL literature or in
um I don't know some other
resources but yeah I agree that
sometimes it can at times it can be
confusing because uh elbow is basically
the negative variation of free energy
right so
um yeah that's exactly almost exactly
the same concept
yeah and then um uh
Martin you asked the chat can surprise
be lowered through action well yes these
are the two ways to to minimize free
energy
change your mind perception learning
change the world through Action Now
action cannot directly reduce your
surprise about sensory outcomes so let's
just think about body temperature we
expect and prefer 37.
we're getting surprised because we're at
40.
now no action is going to pick up the
temperature and move it back to 37. but
in action
May influence the world turning on the
air conditioner or taking off the jacket
so that future sensory observations are
minimally surprising
and that's exactly
what equation 2.6 describes
which is we're going to evaluate
future courses of action turn on the air
conditioner or don't these are our two
policy options
evaluate these two alternative policies
in terms of
two different
criteria
what we stand to learn
here
y tilde is the only difference between
these two double lines the KL Divergence
that's what you're taking the Divergence
between
so if y tilde gave you no information
then this KL Divergence would be
zero
so if the policy doesn't bring you any
if the new observations don't bring you
information the informational gain is
zero
whereas if you stand to learn a lot from
the observations that you expect to get
under that policy the the informational
gain or the epistemic value is high
pragmatic value is about the alignment
of observations with your preferences
and so actions are selected
prospectively
in order to
um balance the price
but that also includes this epistemic
components
so it's not just like the kind of dark
room well then why don't we just close
our eyes and you know
curl up
because
Things become more surprising while
you're not looking
so informational gain is still part of
the picture
but yes absolutely
and that's why it's self-evidizing is
this kind of like unifying imperative
that helps us understand the real-time
flow
of belief updating and sensory
perception on one hand
and extends that prospectively
into the actions to let action selection
case with expected free energy
so can surprise we lowered their action
not directly
however actions are selected
prospectively based on their causal
efficacy in the world
with the imperative of bounding surprise
about those observations Darius
yes I recognize um I may be jumping the
gun on this and maybe we will come to it
but um
in order to select uh perspective action
policies so as to minimize future free
energy presumably
is to run the sort of causal regression
back there has to be some trials
um regarding the probability of that
policy reducing free energy so my
question is according to the active
inference framework
what are the initial priors that govern
um action and I'm talking even here at a
very sort of Developmental level
um I imagine that genetics has a role to
play but is there also just a picking
out of good outcomes initially on
basically randomness
yeah
yes this is a very a very uh good
question and it speaks like some of the
the challenging aspects of modeling
which is what do you explicitly versus
implicitly bake into the model
so this is like looking a little bit
ahead to figure seven three it's the
same as figure 4.3 basically
the um
causal efficacies in the world are
captured by the B Matrix
if I do policy one versus policy two how
is that going to change hidden States
and then hidden States emit observations
so how do Agents come to know
that turning on the air conditioner
reduces the temperature or that putting
on jacket increases the temperature
so that's the question of of the B
Matrix Being Fit obviously if your B
Matrix were washed out
action would be meaningless like if you
didn't if if you didn't know or if your
actions didn't have any consequence then
action selection is kind of for naught
and then depending on on the situation
you could think about B being inherited
like inherited prior or like the first
prior potentially developmentally
also B can be lurked so the consequences
of action can be learned from an
initially plastic B
Ollie
actually this is a question that's been
asked time I mean over and over again uh
has kind of criticism for active
inference framework regarding how
exactly those prior beliefs
um emerge from so
um I mean uh talking a bit more uh
theoretically philosophically or even
more fundamentally uh well fep
starts from the priest's opposition that
there is an agent or a particle with a
certain internal States and then
attempts to describe the geometry of the
information uh that's been related to
the interaction between those internal
States and the external States through
Markov blanket so fep by itself doesn't
say anything about how those internal
States
emerge from at the first place of course
it provides an account for the
self-organization
through I mean describing
um
uh describing the process that such
internal states can increasingly get
more complicated becoming higher
dimensional and so on but I mean by
itself it doesn't provide any account uh
for any explanation for the emergence of
those uh internal states of the first
place so if we take that as uh the basic
premise of the active inference I mean
as a precondition for
the application of fep then I think this
question or this criticism can be
resolved uh because obviously fpp never
attempts to provide anything more than
it claims right so yeah that's uh I
think
one of the crucial points that we need
to keep in mind uh regarding what
exactly the are the claims of are the
theoretical and empirical claims of FTP
and active improvements
awesome and this this reminds me of the
uh delightful
actual constants
um argument
the free energy principle it's not about
what it takes it's about what took you
there
if you're ready for some
um philosophical tongue twisters
the free energy principle is not
concerned with the conditions of
existence
so not what has to be the case for
something to exist that's an ontological
analysis
but
rather with what must have been the case
given that a thing exists
so the presupposition of there being a
thing is what Ali highlighted it's not
about figuring out what it takes to be
alive again what conditions lead to life
flip it
it's about a system of interest and
understanding what must have happened
for that system of interest to have been
that way
which is self-evidently behavior
so it's not that self-evidencing
behavior begets life necessarily
although that also may be true
it's that
things that are persistent
whether they're inert and simple or
conservative
um active systems or even strange
sophisticated cognitive systems
whatever level of complexity
the thing is
we're going to be able to do this kind
of fep or active inference analysis
but that doesn't mean that this is a
forward-looking analysis about what it
takes to be alive
but this is an excellent work by Axel
okay cool let's continue through these
questions but these are these are fun
page 22 the results of inference are not
necessarily accurate in any objective
sense
for a number of reasons biological
creatures operate on the basis of
limited computational and energetic
resources ultimately as all computers do
too
with these limitations influence the
strength of priors
in addition to confidence and thus
minimize Bayesian surprise
for example observations might give rise
to surprise but the generative model is
not updated
uh due to the inferred energetic or
cognitive costs of updating practical
examples being not wanting to change an
opinion because doing so requires
investment of time
uh to thank discern
Etc
yeah I think it's it's a great Insight
people can feel free to add
um
however
strategy selection cognitive strategy
selection
may or may not have ultimate accuracy as
it's imperative
as the question highlights
whether it's a energy ultimately
energetic cost or it's some type of like
psychological or energy or cognitive
cost of updating or even a Time cost
or an uncertainty cost or a social
penalty type cost
[Music]
um
there are a whole host of reasons
that an update could be considered
Bayesian optimal
and not
fully or only align
with the most accurate
account
Darius
just a question what hope to mine was
might that not be the minimization of
prediction error or free energy at a
higher level of the hierarchy so I may
not want to change my mind because of
social pressures in turn fulfilling my
prediction that I will not be socially
ostracized so will a Bayesian with an
optimal Bayesian inference engine
might this still be optimal it's just
that we're getting skewed by looking
maybe not holistically at the the entire
hierarchy
yes this is exactly exactly it like how
how can um
um even pathological or or harmful
Behavior be understood as Bayes optimal
and and the answer there is given the
setup of the generative model the prior
is the way they are and the state
um transition inference is the way they
are the attention the way it is then
name your DSM condition it is a Bayes
optimal
given the totality of the cognitive
model
and so it's it's not like some behavior
is is
um like let's just say rational or
irrational
they're all doing optimal Bayesian
inference the ball is rolling downhill
now you might not like where the ball
rolls or Society may say that the ball
should have gone this way not that way
but
it's all like water flowing to the
bottom of the hill or the ball rolling
to the bottom of the hill
on the landscape
and that's optimal Bayesian inference
so that's that's a totally
great on point and they'll talk more
about
um
like optimalities measured in relation
to expected free energy
well if you have a distorted perception
of how things are happening in the world
then that agent's optimal selection
again doesn't mean that the payoff is
going to be the highest
it just means that it's it's a
optimality concept
that's
um agentic
so optimal Bayesian inference doesn't
mean
best of all possible worlds
all the agent does is when you know
Fitness is optimized the game theory is
transcended optimal basing inference
just means given the generative model
the ball rolls down the hill
and so if you account for
for example higher order considerations
then you you can end up with what might
otherwise be seen as like aberrant
or pathological Behavior
so for example um uh
uh being unable to
um uh confidently predict the reactions
of others in a social setting
might lead one to pursue
um a sort of um
self-oriented Behavior
because it has understandable
predictable consequences like
self-stimulation
again that's not to say that that it's
optimal in terms of social reward
received
it's just under the optimality Criterion
that generative models are actually
playing out under
all neurodiversity
Beyond humans even just cognitive
diversity is being modeled with this
optimal Bayesian framework
but connecting back to the um
cybernetics good regulator theorem and
requisite diversity
while it's true the results of inference
are not necessarily accurate
over
the developmental or evolutionary time
scales
at least the results of inference have
to be adequate enough
to keep you in the game
otherwise you're very quickly going to
be swept off the table
so that's kind of this qualified
pragmatism scientific realism
like it it's not
[Music]
um
not trying to paint
how it really is out there but
causal architectures of the external
World though they're not directly
observable
have to be at least understood well
enough in order to make adaptive
decision making in a dissipative or
adversarial niche
well actually
um what you described accounts for a
pathology without Insight when the
patient suffers and knows something is
off
I am not sure it's described this way
pathology with Insight present
depression
yeah meta cognition
okay
prediction error surprise variational
free energy
these terms are related to one another
but sometimes the relations are not
immediately clear causing some confusion
the common objective of perception
action can be formalized as a
minimization of the discrepancy
sometimes this is operationalized in
terms of prediction error when is the
discrepancy not operationalized as a
prediction error
if we calculate surprise as per page 19
is this a different
um than the calculation for related
terms what is the possible confusion in
interchangeably using these terms
okay I'll give a thought but but I'll
hear anyone else please feel free
um
prediction error
is like the simple differential or the
simple discrepancy
I thought it was going to be 10 it came
in at 11 so the the simple discrepancy
was
this amount of units
of temperature
thought it was going to be 10 degrees
came in at 11. the prediction error was
plus one unit of temperature
in contrast surprise is an information
theoretic quantity it's measured in Nats
or in bits but surprise is like looking
at the distribution how surprising
is that given observation kind of like a
z-score in statistics like oh this was
three standard deviations
now it may be the case that one degree
temperature is one standard deviation
and so it was one standard deviation a
surprise for that plus one prediction
error
and then
variational free energy
is
um shown in equation 2.5
they're related to each other
because it where the prediction error is
zero
surprise is minimized but not
necessarily zero
they're still non-zero surprise
associated with picking the exact
highest point on the gaussian
minimized surprise but not zero surprise
and similarly picking that exact
midpoint on the gaussian would minimize
variational free energy okay I thought
that the classroom was four feet plus or
minus one I pull a height it's four feet
so it's a minimal surprise minimizing
free energy
minimizing prediction error
so they're kind of all
um colleagues
and helping us point to to different
aspects
of model fit
but they're not the exact same quantity
Ali and then anyone else
also it relates to the difference
between the exact Bayesian inference and
the approximate Bayesian inference
because uh basically when we talk about
free energy
it refers to the exact amount of the
surprisal that needs to be minimized but
when we talk about variation of free
energy
we uh we utilize the approximate
Bayesian inference
techniques in order to come up with a
bound or more precisely an upper bound
to minimize the surprise so it's not the
exact Bayesian inference because it
would be track intractable and most real
world situations but rather it provides
an alternative way of
dealing with the complex situations by
providing an upper Bound for the
surprisal namely the variational free
energy uh also uh I think it might I
mean it might be helpful to
point out uh the paper by alirezamodu
shanichi which provides 14 different
definitions for the surprisal in
different contexts so
we also had a guest stream with
aneurizoma dushanichi which I recommend
watching and looking up that paper as
well
yeah this was very
um very rich paper and stream and
discussion where they derived I think
yeah how many 18 or 14.
surprise Concepts
included and show you know
again just intuitively if your model is
fitting as well as possible if the
evidence is the highest
you'd be right to expect that surprise
would be lowest in general
but it turns out that there's actually a
plethora of ways that surprise is
computed
and they're they're not exactly
equivalent
and and we expect that many other
ontology terms attention
anticipation all these kinds of terms
where we have a broad everyday sense of
the term
and then we also make technical
definitions of them in the active
inference ontology many other terms may
have also
um just like words in the dictionary
have multiple bylights
great question though
okay
all right
equation 2.6 so the trade-off between
Information Gain
let's copy it in
you trade off between Information Gain
and pragmatic value is quite
understandable
so that's referring to this kind of Top
Line classical decomposition of expected
free energy
this is our unified imperative
for Action selection
which is we should select policies
based upon
their pragmatic and epistemic value
so
not to talk about the other guys but in
reward Centric learning
you need to coerce epistemic value into
pragmatic value
because it's like a single currency of
of pragmatism or reward so you have
reward itself and he said well it's it's
worthwhile to go on this little
exploration because the expected reward
or the expected utility is such and such
so I I would you rather have one dollar
on the ground now or ten percent chance
of a hundred by going on this
exploration and so reward learning would
go on that
um route depending on some risk
discounting which we'll we'll look at
whereas an expected free energy
we're just jointly considering both the
epistemic and the pragmatic
now we're going to look at some
different
decompositions of G
how expected ambiguity and risk interact
or are counterbalanced is quite hard to
be understood can anyone provide a good
explanation
okay
so does anyone want to give a thought on
how would they read
um
the second line
and I think we'll all look forward to
um
the derivations and also look to improve
the the natural language descriptions
with just like the verbatim readings
um but what what does anyone see in this
second line
I'll I'll just give a thought so H is
entropy so this is how blurry or sharp a
distribution is is captured by its
entropy
so
the first term expected ambiguity
here we have a distribution of
observations through a Time y tilde
given hidden states to talk
so this is like
how entropic
how um
um sharply defined
will observations be so you can imagine
a super if there's two outcomes
it's going to be really ambiguous if
both the outcomes have this have
um messy observations
you know whether we win or lose if we're
getting this static on the radio
then the ambiguity is high
whereas
this term is going to be
um favoring policies that lead to
unambiguous resolution
[Music]
of the relationship between hidden
States and sensory data
so here the kind of sub imperative
is pursue policies big fancy e
expectation
pursue policies that have
um less ambiguous expected
entropies
this so so this is just sensory this is
only about the mapping between the
hidden States or time and the sensory
observations
um that are happening through time
the second term
we have the KL Divergence double line
on the left side of the parentheses are
the sensory observations Through Time
and so it's the difference between the
sensory observations condition on what
we do
and the sensory observations conditioned
on what we prefer
C
um
so
this is risk not in the danger sense
specifically
but rather a risky outcome or a risky
policy is one that leads to
um a range of outcomes
a non-risky policy is one that Maps
tightly to a certain outcome
so this expected ambiguity term
helps us
um pursue policies
that give unambiguous sensory data about
hidden states of the world
and this risk term helps us pursue
policies
that are causal intervention has
efficacy in
the uh
um being able to shape
sensory outcomes
this next
yeah Andrew
uh I just wanted to say it the the most
health prior to your explanation for
understanding these terms were just the
simple examples given in textbooks so so
with ambiguity they give the example of
like
the probability of heads or tails in the
coin flip conditioned on whether it is
sunny or raining will be maximally
ambiguous is there's no relationship
between the weather and the 50 50 chance
of heads or tails so
um it seems to relate to something like
independence of events uh in that case I
mean it's entirely independent you know
the result of your coin flip and
um very distinct and it doesn't provide
you any useful information about the
other scenario
um and then with with risk
um similarly to what you were saying uh
the kind of one-to-many mapping between
policies and outcomes for example a
highly risky policy uh or action is
related to uh playing a slot machine you
know or say you have a slot machine that
has like three potential outcomes each
with equivalent you know probability is
oh I do this one action but there are a
variety of outcomes you know that could
come out of this and so there's very
high risk uh to your action as opposed
to you know
um holding a slot machine and having a
guaranteed win every time
nice awesome
uh I actually wrote down this question
because
I got a bit confused about
um well so policies that seem to be uh
reducing the ambiguity also seems to
reduce the risks so like it made me kind
of confused because well both both
values would be would be heading towards
the same policy so it doesn't seem like
it's a trade-off at all
so
um compared to the information gain and
pragmatic value which seems to be very
intuitively and create a trade-off
uh I couldn't catch the um uh
a good example or a good explanation
about how these two values expected
ambiguity and risks are interacting with
each other
that's a very very good point
um although explore exploit is kind of
like a classical trade-off and it's one
that's going to be approached in the
book like
um you could imagine situations where
there's two policies and one of them
gives more epistemic value and pragmatic
value and similarly you could imagine
situations where they are
um in trade-off or attention
and so similarly it would be helpful to
think of examples like real or contrived
um where ambiguity and risk are are
aligned or not Ollie what do you think
you're you're immediately or
I'm sorry oh yeah can you hear me now
okay
uh all right so the expected free energy
somehow unifies uh various accounts of
um resolving the ambiguity from
different uh disciplines and different
um I mean from several with Townsend
psychology machine learning and so on so
for instance uh
accounting for the risk both in terms of
outcomes and in terms of States uh is
inspired from a common and diversky's
work on
the risk sensitive policies as applied
to economics and also the Callback
Library control engineering so here uh
actually minimizing the risk somehow
course pounds it corresponds to aligning
our predictions to our prior preferences
but well in in the absence of um
the risk all we have is just the
ambiguity uh that uh that that is
basically accounted for in the accounts
from uh James and also Lindley uh in
which uh they they only account for the
resolving of the uncertainties through
uh the uh through diminishing the
ambiguities and not accounting for the
risk implied in each situation uh so uh
I think we're short on time but it can
be explained uh in a bit more detail how
exactly uh those uh three or four lines
of equations can be related to each
other and uh how each of them
corresponds with some of the other
accounts of uh how how we can resolve
those ambiguities and uncertainties
through different techniques but
um
nonetheless expected free energy uh to
the best of my knowledge is I mean
provides uh the most all-encompassing
and unified way of accounting for all of
these
um various techniques of reducing the
uncertainty but we can talk about that a
bit more in the next session I guess
yeah thank you Ali
figure 2.6
summarizes a few of those threads
it shows how like in the absence of
pragmatic value
what you're left with
is an information
seeking imperative conversely in the
absence of epistemic gain
you're left with
naked epistemic utility Theory
and under another restricted subset kind
of special case of G
you end up with risk sensitive policy
which is part of that common inversky
um line of work
um well
glad that we were able to get to the uh
um cohort 4 chapter 2
questions
uh next week we will be a different time
but we'll continue on chapter two so
whether you'll be able to be here or not
please feel free to add more questions
in and and uh upvote other
questions I mean there's almost 50
questions but please please add up votes
and we'll uh
um
improve the discourse and maybe record
some short videos and and continue these
great topics
um
as we proceed along the low road so
thank you everybody
see you next time
bye thank you thank you